A Finding Aid to the State of the Arts Videorecordings, 1979, in the Archives of American Art AAA.frailawr
Archives of American Art
State of the arts videorecordings
1979
AAA.frailawr
Archives of American Art
2.4 Linear feet
The State of the Arts videorecordings measure 2.4 linear feet and consist of 30 videocassettes (U-matic) and three sets of handwritten notes, all created during the production of a pilot episode for a broadcast television documentary series on contemporary art in 1979. Four stories were produced for the pilot: a staged debate on modern art at the Museum of Modern Art; an investigation into the economics of the contemporary art market, a collaboration between video artist Nam June Paik and sound artist Liz Phillips, and an extended interview with sculptor George Segal on the occasion of his 1979 retrospective exhibition at the Whitney Museum of American Art. Video footage includes raw footage for each segment and edited versions of the economics of art story, the Nam June Paik and Liz Phillips story, and the George Segal story. The reporter and interviewer for the program was Barry Nolan.
Lawrence P. Fraiberg Productions.
Biographical/Historical note
State of the Arts was planned as a broadcast television magazine program on the subject of contemporary art. The pilot was produced in 1979 by Lawrence P. Fraiberg Productions with funding provided jointly by IBM and the National Endowment for the Arts. Fraiberg and Tom Cavanau served as executive co-producers, Rick Derman as field producer, and Barry Nolan as interviewer. The program never aired.
Lawrence P. Fraiberg was a longtime television documentary veteran when the pilot was produced. He graduated from the University of California in 1949 and began his career at television station KPIX in San Francisco. He became vice president and general manager of WNEW-TV in New York in 1965, and was named president of Metromedia Television in 1977. In 1980 he was appointed president of the Television Station Group for Westinghouse Broadcasting. An active member in community and industry organizations, he is a recipient of an honorary degree (1978) from St. John's University, New York, a Peabody Award for Lifetime Achievement in the Broadcasting Industry (1986), and a Trustees Award from the National Academy of Television Arts and Sciences (1990). He died in 2011.
Barry Nolan, the interviewer for State of the Arts, went on to a career as a television magazine host and producer, with credits including Evening Magazine, Hard Copy, Extra!, and Nitebeat, and in 2012 produced the documentary No Way Out But One with his wife, Garland Waller.
Arrangement note
The collection is arranged as one series.
Series 1: State of the Arts Production Video, 1979 (2.4 linear feet; boxes 1-3)
Conditions Governing Access note
Use of original papers requires an appointment and is limited to the Archives’ Washington, D.C. Research Center. Use of archival audiovisual recordings with no duplicate access copy requires advance notice. Contact Reference Services for more information.
Immediate Source of Acquisition note
Donated 1979-1980 by Lawrence P. Fraiberg.
Scope and Contents note
The State of the Arts videorecordings measure 2.4 linear feet and consist of 30 videocassettes (U-matic) and three sets of handwritten notes, all created during the production of a pilot episode for a broadcast television documentary series on contemporary art in 1979. Four stories were produced for the pilot: a staged debate on modern art at the Museum of Modern Art; an investigation into the economics of the contemporary art market, a collaboration between video artist Nam June Paik and sound artist Liz Phillips, and an extended interview with sculptor George Segal on the occasion of his 1979 retrospective exhibition at the Whitney Museum of American Art. Video footage includes raw footage for each segment and edited versions of the economics of art story, the Nam June Paik and Liz Phillips story, and the George Segal story. The reporter and interviewer for the program was Barry Nolan.
Although the program never aired, the video shot for the pilot documents significant artists and gallerists of its time, with profiles of O.K. Harris Works of Art and its founder, Ivan Karp, as well as art dealer Holly Solomon and critic Barbara Rose, Marcia Tucker in the early days of the New Museum, and footage of artists like Nam June Paik, Liz Phillips, and George Segal in their studios, describing their work in detail. The sound and video piece created by Paik and Phillips with the dancer Robert Kovich was commissioned by the State of the Arts producers for the pilot program, and the four hours of video documenting their collaboration and its product may therefore be unique.
Interview subjects for the economics of art story include Ivan Karp, Tom Drysdale, Rick Derman, Cosmo Campoli, Joan Thorne, Holly Solomon, Marcia Tucker, and Barbara Rose. The Marcia Tucker interview takes place at the New School, which was at the time the home of the New Museum. Footage also includes a gallery opening at O.K. Harris Works of Art. Extended interviews with Liz Phillips, Nam June Paik, and George Segal are found in the footage of their respective stories.
Campoli, Cosmo; Cavanau, Ted; Derman, Rick; Fraiberg, Lawrence P.; Karp, Ivan C., 1926-; Kovich, Robert; Lawrence P. Fraiberg Productions.; Museum of Modern Art (New York, N.Y.).; New Museum. (New York, N.Y.); Nolan, Barry; OK Harris Gallery.; Paik, Nam June, 1932-2006; Phillips, Liz; Rose, Barbara; Segal, George, 1924-2000; Solomon, Holly; Thorne, Joan, 1943-; Whitney Museum of American Art.; Art critics; Art dealers; Art galleries, Commercial--New York (State)--New York; Art museum directors--New York (State)--New York--Interviews; Art, Modern--20th century--Study and teaching; Art--Economic aspects; Artists' studios; Artists--Interviews; Gallery owners--Interviews; Interviews; Performance art; Sculptors--New Jersey--Interviews; Sound sculpture--United States; Video art--United States; Video artists; Video recordings; Women artists; Women museum curators--New York (State)--New York--Interviews; Women sculptors--Interviews
- State of the Arts Production Video, 1979; Series 1; 2.4 Linear feet Boxes 1-3
  Scope and Contents note
  Series contains 30 videocassettes (U-matic) made for the State of the Arts television series pilot created in 1979. Footage from the production of four separate stories are found, including a staged debate on modernism in art between Martin Abend and Peter Fengesten at the Museum of Modern Art, a story on the economics of art with interviews of artists and gallerists, documentation of a collaboration between sound artist Liz Phillips and video artist Nam June Paik, and a story on the 1979 retrospective of George Segal, shot during its exhibition at the Whitney Museum of American Art.
  Video shot for the “Economics of Art” story includes candid interviews regarding how money is spent and made in the contemporary art market of 1979, including as interview subjects Ivan Karp, Tom Drysdale, Rick Derman, Cosmo Campoli, Joan Thorne, Holly Solomon, Marcia Tucker, and Barbara Rose. Interviews with Liz Phillips, Nam June Paik, and George Segal are found in the unedited footage of their respective stories. In addition to interviews, unedited footage contains staged interactions and sequences, footage of studios and galleries, artists and gallerists at work, and footage of a 1979 opening at the OK Harris gallery. Edited versions of the “Economics of Art” story, the Liz Phillips and Nam June Paik collaboration, and the George Segal retrospective story are also found at the end of each group.
  Handwritten notes containing lists of questions asked in interviews are found for the OK Harris Gallery Interviews and the Marcia Tucker interview at the New Museum, and a list of visual shots is found for the George Segal story describing the Whitney Museum footage.
  Arrangement note
  Videocassettes are arranged by story subject.
  - Debate on Modern Art between Martin Abend and Peter Fengesten at MoMA, 1979 September 13-14; 2 Videocassettes (U-matic) (Box 1, Folder 1)
    Cassette 2 begins with a few minutes of footage showing Holly Solomon Gallery interior views from "The Economics of Art" story.
  - "The Economics of Art" Story (Box 1)
    - O.K. Harris Gallery and Interviews, 1979 September 4; 3 Videocassettes (U-matic) Includes handwritten list of interview questions and shot list (Box 1, Folder 2-4)
    - Marcia Tucker at the New School, 1979 September 10; 4 Videocassettes (U-matic) Includes handwritten list of interview questions and shot list (Box 1, Folder 5-7)
    - Edited Story, 1979; 2 Videocassettes (U-matic) (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Nam June Paik and Liz Phillips Collaboration Story (Box 1)
    - Liz Phillips Studio and Interview, 1979 September 17; 2 Videocassettes (U-matic) (Box 1, Folder 9)
      2 of 5 videocassettes
  - Nam June Paik and Liz Phillips Collaboration Story (Box 2)
    - Liz Phillips Studio and Interview, 1979 September 17; 3 Videocassettes (U-matic) (Box 2, Folder 1-2)
      3 of 5 videocassettes
    - Nam June Paik Studio and Interview, and Artists Synthesizing Video and Sound, 1979 September 18; 3 Videocassettes (U-matic) (Box 2, Folder 3-4)
    - Video and Sound Synthesis, 1979; 3 Videocassettes (U-matic) (Box 2, Folder 5-6)
      The second half of cassette 3 of 3 contains an edited version of the Lip Phillips and Robert Kovich interviews and studio footage.
    - Edited Story, 1979; 1 Videocassettes (U-matic) (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - George Segal Retrospective Story (Box 2)
    - George Segal Studio and Interview, 1979 September 5; 2 Videocassettes (U-matic) (Box 2, Folder 8)
      2 of 4 videocassettes
  - George Segal Retrospective Story (Box 3)
    - George Segal Studio and Interview, 1979 September 5; 2 Videocassettes (U-matic) (Box 3, Folder 1)
    - Whitney Museum Footage, 1979 September 6; 2 Videocassettes (U-matic) Includes handwritten shot list (Box 3, Folder 2)
    - Edited Story, 1979; 1 Videocassettes (U-matic) tape labeled "Protection Dub" (Box 3, Folder 3)